A Guide to the Ethel Bailey Furman, Papers and architectural drawings, 1928-2003
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Ethel Bailey Furman, Papers and architectural drawings, 1928-2003
Library of Virginia
41145
108 sheets (mostly tracing paper and graphite, some blueprints and Diazo prints, 92 x 61 cm. and smaller), 38 leaves, 1 sound recording
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. J. Livingston Furman, Richmond, Virginia, 26 February 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
Ethel Bailey Furman (1893-1976), probably the first practicing African-American female architect in Virginia, studied architecture with a private tutor in New York City circa 1915 and at the Chicago Technical Institute from 1944-1946. A Richmond native and daughter of a promient African-American builder, for many years she worked out of the home built by her father, Madison J. Furman, at 3025 Q Street. She is credited with nearly two hundred public and private designs in Richmond and the surrounding area, including Fair Oak Baptist Church (Richmond, Virginia), St. James Baptist Church (Goochland County, Virginia), the Robert J. Wilder home (Richmond, Virginia), and Mount Nebo Baptist Church (New Kent County, Virginia). Furman was active in a number of civic organizations and church groups. Two of the architect's designs were donated to the Lott Carey Missionary League and were erected in Liberia, Africa. Ethel Bailey Furman died in Richmond on Tuesday, February 24, 1976.
Scope and Content
This accession consists of architectural drawings and plans, newspaper clippings, photographs, a research paper, and ephemera related to the life and career of Ethel Madison Bailey Furman. Research shows Furman to be the first practicing female African-American architect in the Commonwealth of Virginia.
Series I: Papers, 1928-2003, consists primarily of items collected by her son, J. Livingston Furman, relating to or written about Ethel Bailey Furman's career. The folder contains a photograph of the architect at the 1928 "Negro Contractors' Conference" at Hampton Institute, an invoice from M. J. Bailey, an article from the Pittsburgh Courier on Furman, various modern-day photographs of Furman buildings, and sundry ephemera. The materials also include a research paper and prints of slides researched and written by Jessica Breeden for the American Institute of Architects lecture at Fourth Baptist Church in Richmond, Virginia, on April 16, 1997. A sound recording of the presentation is also contained in this series. Unfortunately, the majority of Ms. Furman's early drawings, client correspondence, and other business materials were lost during a household move necessitated by failing health in her latter years. This collection represents all of the surviving materials from Ethel Bailey Furman's architectural practice.
Series II: Drawings, 1939-1976, consists of pencil and tracing paper drawings for public and private structures designed by Furman during latter part of her architectural practice. This series makes up the bulk of the collection. The buildings depicted were designed for middle- and upper middle-class African-American families and religious institutions. Of particular note are the numerous commissions for the Snead family of Goochland County.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series. Series I: Papers, 1928-2003, is organized alphabetically by folder title. Series II: Drawings, 1939-1976, is arranged alphabetically by client and chronologically thereunder.
Contents List
- Papers, 1928-2003
  - Papers, 1928-2003, 38 leaves
    contains a photograph of the architect at the 1928 "Negro Contractors' Conference" at Hampton Institute, an invoice from M. J. Bailey, an article from the Pittsburgh Courier on Furman, various modern-day photographs of Furman buildings, and sundry ephemera. The materials also include a research paper and prints of slides researched and written by Jessica Breeden for the American Institute of Architects lecture at Fourth Baptist Church in Richmond, Virginia, on April 16, 1997. A sound recording of the presentation is also contained in this series.
- Drawings, 1939-1976, Tracing paper, Diazo prints, blueprints.
  Alphabetically by client and chronologically thereunder.
  - Apostolic Faith Church, - Church - n.d., Dimensions: 73 x 45 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 3 (Folder 1)
    Location: Richmond, VA
  - Bazemore, John J.- Residence - n.d., Dimensions: 67.5 x 44 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Blueprints; Sheets: 9 (Folder 1, Folder 2)
  - Cauthorne, Leland S.- Residence - n.d., Dimensions: 81.5 x 50 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 4 (Folder 1, Folder 3)
    Location: Goochland, VA
  - Cedar Street Memorial Baptist Church, - Church - n.d., Dimensions: 48 x 36 cm.; Scale: 1/2" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 3 (Folder 1, Folder 4)
    Location: Goochland Co, VA
  - Dickerson, Isaac- Residence - ca. 1950, Dimensions: 69 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 4 (Folder 1, Folder 5)
  - Edwards, Thomas N.- Residence - ca. 1950, Dimensions: 70 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 3 (Folder 1, Folder 6)
    Location: Chesterfield County, VA
  - Fourth Baptist Church, - Church - 1961, Dimensions: 89.5 x 51 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 6 (Folder 1, Folder 7)
  - Mt. Carmel Church, - Church - 1955, Dimensions: 71 x 50 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 3 (Folder 1, Folder 8)
    Location: Noel, VA
  - Mt. Nebo Baptist Church, - Church - n.d., Dimensions: 73 x 46 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 5 (Folder 1, Folder 9)
    Location: New Kent Co, VA
  - Mt. Olive Baptist Church, - Church - 1974, Dimensions: 92 x 61 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: Diazo print; Sheets: 6 (Folder 1, Folder 10)
    Location: Henrico Co, VA
  - Mt. Olivet Baptist Church, - Church - n.d., Dimensions: 90 x 60.5 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: Diazo print; Sheets: 3 (Folder 1, Folder 11)
    Location: [no location given],
  - Mt. Pleasant Baptist Church, - Church - n.d., Dimensions: 72.5 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 3 (Folder 1, Folder 12)
    Location: Bermuda Hundred, Chesterfield County, VA
  - Pleasant, Nathan- Residence - ca. 1950, Dimensions: 71.5 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 4 (Folder 1, Folder 13)
    Location: Powhattan, VA
  - Rising Mt. Zion Baptist Church, - Church - 1976, Dimensions: 77.5 x 46 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 5 (Folder 1, Folder 14)
    Location: Sandston, VA
  - Snead, Edward- Residence - 1968, Dimensions: 71 x 38 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 4 (Folder 2, Folder 15)
  - Snead, James- Residence - 1968, Dimensions: 67.5 x 44 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 4 (Folder 2, Folder 16)
  - Snead, Junius- Residence - 1965, Dimensions: 76 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 4 (Folder 2, Folder 17)
    Location: Glen Allen, VA
  - Snead, Mack- Residence - 1968, Dimensions: 73.5 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 4 (Folder 2, Folder 18)
  - Snead, Samuel- Residence - n.d., Dimensions: 68.5 x 46 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 5 (Folder 2, Folder 19)
  - Snead, Thomas M.- Residence - ca. 1968, Dimensions: 68 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 3 (Folder 2, Folder 20)
  - Springfield Baptist Church, - Church - 1976, Dimensions: 67 x 38 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 1 (Folder 2, Folder 21)
    Location: Hanover Co, VA
  - St. James Baptist Church, - Church - 1972, Dimensions: 82 x 68.5 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 5 (Folder 2, Folder 22)
  - St. James Baptist Church, - Church - n.d., Dimensions: 75.5 x 58 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 2 (Folder 2, Folder 23)
    Location: Beaverdam, VA
  - St. James Holiness Church, - Church - 1939, Dimensions: 72.5 x 46.5 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 6 (Folder 2, Folder 24)
  - St. James Holiness Church, - Church - 1956, Dimensions: 65 x 38 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 3 (Folder 2, Folder 25)
  - Union Baptist Church, - Church - n.d., Dimensions: 71.5 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 5 (Folder 2, Folder 26)
    Location: Quinton, VA
  - Union Hope Baptist Church, - Church - n.d., Dimensions: 68.5 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1/4" = 1'; Media: Tracing paper, graphite; Sheets: 1 (Folder 2, Folder 27)
    Location: King William, VA